[Music]
w
hello good evening and good day good day
everybody and welcome back to the ask
show today we are doing episode 130 is
it 2:30 it's episode 2:30 right so uh
today is going to be a video chat live
stream I'm going to open up the links
for uh you to chat with me right here on
the screen in video format let me put
that link right away on the live chat so
here you have it it's it's there now and
let me put it on the
top here we have it okay the video chat
link is live you can join and you can
ask me your questions let's put some
rules on the uh for the video chat so
please keep your questions short and
only one question per person that's it
so that everybody as many people as
possible can get the chance to ask
questions before that let's see what who
all is there on the live chat I can see
young Sonic Rin D abishek crazy brain
hello abanu Sharma 142 yadesh
poar uh gorov Mr
88 paparo Mansa
badas RI Kumar lobzang
shitang shitang Tes
B uh honey Arian saavan Priyanka javala
grimo bad AIT Singh korana geopolitical
dub hello vaj deshmuk ADI Singh Dr sen
young Sonic chatres Kap akit
suas lakshman Crick lover mcloven hello
honey Ria dilep graphic designer
Priyanka again utsav katri Sayan go SRI
Hara and so many other people so uh yes
I have opened up the live chat for
everybody and it can take 15 people at a
time so people will have to be uh a
little bit
patient so let's let's G get going and
let's take some questions let's see who
all is there I can see a lot of people
let us go with our friend Raji hello
hello sir how are you doing hello sir
good
evening even yeah sir my question is
regarding the Korean industry so so
recently we have seen a rise in
popularity of Korean web series movies
due to which the Korean skincare
industry Cosmetics food fashion has seen
a good rise in the Indian market so
taking this as an example my question is
is this kind of a rise organic or is
this manufactured through perhaps a very
clever marketing strategy because the
Korean brands are making a good profit
out of I
assume could you mention some Brands as
an
example uh like for the foods we have
that bulog and all those Noodle Brands
I've seen I don't follow the kin much
but my friends they are ordering
Chopsticks and buying clothes from them
something yeah those rice water serums
and all these things M yeah yeah good
question so the Korean uh brands are
pretty popular across the world not just
in India when it comes to Korean music
we don't understand the Korean language
but it's very popular
especially among certain certain age
demographic in India and even Korean web
series are very popular on Netflix and
whatever else so is it organic is it uh
manufactured uh look Korea is a highly
developed country it's a first world
country so they have high standards uh
they they do have uh a
significantly sophisticated uh movie
making industry and series making and
all all of that film industry and when
it comes to their their products like
noodles and whatnot I mean I'm sure
they're pretty high quality so the
quality is there you don't understand
that first of all the quality is there
now when it comes to
marketing the
Koreans how would they Market themselves
I mean uh they are being marketed by the
Americans essentially see Korea as we
know is a very strong Ally let's say of
the United States the Americans have
more than 100 military based on Korean
soil So Korea is you could say a protect
or a vasal of the US and in exchange and
as a reward for being so good to the US
they will get these perks so that these
are the perks that you get by being a
wasal of of a very powerful Nation if
you tow the line and you do everything
they want you to do you will get a lot
of promotion your people your industries
will do well whatever is allowed uh your
people will get a very good lifestyle
and access to the whole world and so on
so I think the quality is definitely
there but uh why are so many Korean web
series Etc being promoted on Netflix
some of them are definitely really good
was a squid game right it's very very
famous so there is that but I'm sure
there are many of those that are not
probably that good but they're still
being promoted in very large numbers on
Netflix and whatever else uh K-pop
nobody understands the Korean language
but it's still so popular so obviously
there's a push from somewhere uh that's
coming into behind this so it's a
combination of both things
uh it helps to be on the good side of
the US it helps to to be really close to
the us and then you get all these points
so that's the deal and that's why Korean
brands are very popular across the world
all right thank you sir thank you thank
you Raj nice to meet you thank you
bye okay let's take a question from our
friend geopolitical dub hello sir have
Tak lot of your questions yeah good to
see you finally
hello hello thank you sir sir my
question is sir I want to know about the
persecution of Hindus in
Bhutan okay how it all
started okay the persecution of Hindus
in Bhutan so I am not extremely familiar
with this uh topic I am aware of of some
kind of alleged ethnic cleansing that is
said to have happened in the past I'm
not sure uh I've not looked into the
details but apparently there were a
large number of nepales origin Hindus or
other Northern Indian origin Hindus a
large number of those in Bhutan and
maybe in the 80s 70s ' 80s '90s
somewhere around that time they were uh
let's say deported or expelled out of
Bhutan I'm not sure if there was any
violence or not but yeah that's what I
have heard vaguely I am not aware of the
details uh but we should remember that
Bhutan is a friendly country and we want
Bhutan to remain friendly with us and we
obviously have very ancient cultural and
civilizational relations with Bhutan and
Bhutan is under extreme pressure to from
the Chinese to you could say become a
Chinese vasal or protectorate and it is
not good if that happens not for us and
not for Bhutan either so uh that's
that's beside the point beside the point
of when it comes to the question that
you asking but I am not aware of the
specific details of of exactly what has
happened but I've heard these uh I've
heard people speak about this I've not
really investigated and read about this
so that's what I can tell you sir thank
you sir thank you so much and very nice
to see you finally thank
you okay we'll take uh questions let's
see anandu is waiting so hello anandu
sir how you
doing hello sir so happy to be here sir
I'm from Kerala
nice to meet you sir happy to have you
here yeah so my question is very simple
sir the first La of Independence
happened 1857 so 50 years before that in
Kerala there was a king called paraja
his Revol happened in 1788 something and
also there is a dala from his name Isa
his Revol also happened in something
1800s but why this is not called first
war of independence why only particular
1857 that war happened on the part of
Northern side uh up biar jansi Etc it's
not as uh it's not as the first of
Independence and also sir does that at
the particular time why it is contained
in those those areas only why it is not
ex to anywhere else why the history is
always delh entric that's simplest con I
can have yeah you make a good point here
so uh see the history is written by The
Victors and the and when it comes to
Indian history it was written by a very
specific group of people people who had
a very specific agenda as to how to
portray India's history so for the
longest time until until very recently
what happened in 1857 was called the
Great Indian Mutiny or great Indian
Revolt not the first war of independence
okay so even that event which was spread
across very large part parts of India
was portrayed as a mutiny or a Revolt
which sounds like a small thing a mutiny
is typic typically something that
happens on board a ship when the sailors
revolt against the captain that's a
mutiny that's a small number of people
but what happened in 1857 was much
larger than that but our historians our
own historians have portrayed it as some
small Uprising or a Revolt or a mutiny
and when it comes to what you're
pointing out there are many such events
that have happened before that where
where people in various parts of India
even in like you mentioning in Kerala in
other parts of Southern India they took
up arms against the British and uh we
know that they they did not succeed in
the long run but they did take up arms
against the British and uh fight the
British not with nonviolence and ahinsa
but actually fighting them and trying to
evict them from our territory uh but uh
there are many instances like this but
our historians have disregarded them and
tried to sweep these uh these these
facts under the carpet so it is now that
all these things are slowly coming out
in the public domain uh thanks uh to a
large part to social media so people in
various parts of India are doing the
research they're coming up with this
information they're putting it out in
the public domain so I think over time
we need to revisit Indian history a
priority and we need to compile all
these facts together and there were many
wars of Independence and 1857 by was by
no means the first one so I'm glad that
you've pointed this out and you are
absolutely
right
right all right Anand thank you so much
for very nice to see you nice to meet
you okay let us see who else we have uh
I will take uh mat nanju hello sir how
are you doing hello sir sir thank you so
much for picking me really I've been
following you sir so one of my questions
is how uh so I I completely understand
your point of the cism was not there
it's been what do you say glorified sir
but if you look at people like basana
like in our region like Karnataka region
the Ling region so so people talk he was
a guy who was reforming us so uh
according to you how much exactly was
this this cism how much exactly was it I
know it's glorified but can you please
tell me how much exactly it was sure
sure uh so
uh the the true facts are unfortunately
shrouded in mystery okay you are
mentioning basavana who is said to be a
great reformer I am not aware of the
story of Shri basaan so I cannot comment
about that but the main issue that
you're asking about is this issue of
castism did we have castism and to what
extent did we have castism and it is
true yeah exactly and and it's true that
if you go to the 19th century the 20th
century before 1947 even after that uh
there looks like there has been castism
even if you go to rural areas today
there is this this Us and Them sort of
thing discrimination and so on right so
when did this actually
emerge uh you have to understand that
the past 1,000 or so years Indian
Society has been under foreign
occupation okay and when a society is
under foreign occupation it is being
persecuted and brutalized it doesn't
function the way it has organically
evolved to function it functions in a
very different way in all kinds of uh
defects and and and problems enter the
society they become part of the society
and if if this continues for centuries
it becomes part of your culture to so to
say but it was never originally part of
a culture so the question we should be
asking ourselves is this that in the
year 500 AD okay 500 AD what was the
situation like in India in Northern
India Southern India East West India did
we have castism we did not have cism we
had the VNA jati system see even if you
go to places like let's say the UK okay
in in the UK you have these surnames
like Fletcher Thatcher aosi Aerosmith uh
Smith and so on a Fletcher is a person
who uh you know who who installs
feathers on arrows that's that's a
hereditary occupation Thatcher means
somebody who puts U you know uh
thatching of the roofs of houses that's
a hereditary occupation so even in
England and if you go to any other
Society you will have the same thing you
will have these hereditary occupations
that are passed down through in families
and communities so that was the same
thing as the Indian VNA jati system okay
and uh there is nothing wrong with that
any any well functioning Society
organizes itself and there is division
of labor and whenever a certain family
or or Community becomes a a specialist
it starts specializing in certain uh
skills then it will try and ensure that
these skills are passed on in the same
Community or same Clan or family that is
not castism it is just the way the
society was organized organically
naturally uh through C over centuries
and thousands of years now if you go
back let's say 2 and a half thousand
years before today okay we talking about
the morian era so there was this uh
Greek Ambassador who came to to India
his name was me megasthenes and he was
the Ambassador at uh at at the court of
our emperor Chandra Gupta Maia uh and
this was in patliputra and he wrote an
account of Indian Society from a very uh
Technic tactical perspective very
militaristic perspective what kind of
nation is this what are the resources it
has what are the geographical boundaries
like what is the kind of society they
have and so on so he
writes his account is called Inda it is
lost but there are many other accounts
that refer to it that's why the some of
the information has survived so he
writes mastan that Indian Society is
divided into seven classes seven classes
not four we think of the jati Verner
system but in 2 and a half thousand
years before today it was organized in
seven classes so you had Merchants you
had Warriors you had Traders you had uh
uh priests obviously brahans and so so
on so it was
seven seven divisions that he mentioned
I don't remember them all so I you have
to understand that Society organically
and naturally evolves over centuries and
thousands of years but what's happened
in the past 1,000 years is is not
Natural Evolution Society was under
tremendous constraints in the past 1,000
years and lots of defects did enter
Society but we have to understand look
when you have a company I give this
example many times let's take the
example of the company called Apple so
Apple was founded by Steve Jobs and and
and vak right whatever his first name
was and uh until for a certain time it
was under the control of Steve Jobs for
for more or less and it did very well
and then Steve Jobs was expelled from
the from the company and then the
company essentially went to the dogs
okay it it was doing very badly it was
on the verge of bankruptcy and then
Steve Job Steve Jobs comes back and he
takes the company again and and revives
it so when the company was performing
very badly it almost went bankrupt who
was at fault was it the employees or was
it the leadership it's always the
leadership right that you will blame for
a company going to the dogs so similarly
when India and Indian Society got so
many defects that entered into it in the
past Thousand Years who was ruling India
you to ask that question our society was
not designed in this manner so yes we
have issues any society has issues today
we have issues that are the consequence
of the past 1,000 years of foreign
occupation and brutalization India is a
society that suffers from Amnesia and
PTSD post-traumatic stress disorder but
because we have also Amnesia because our
historians don't write the truth so we
don't know how all these all these
problems happened so that's the point I
would like to make that you know we
don't know exactly how much whether
there was cast or not as far as we know
there was there wasn't that and whatever
divisions of society existed they
evolved organically like they do in
every other Society but our historians
they make us feel that there is
something inherently wrong with our
society and civilization that we are a
very backward and all that Civilization
which is absolutely wrong we are one of
we are probably the best civilization
that ever existed so that's what I like
to say to you in in response to your
question a very good question sir thank
you so much yes sir sir just one short
just many questions as I'm an
engineering student I'm really
curious no followup question because
there are lots of people waiting in the
line hundreds of people who want to do
the live CH so I'll only take one
question to person but you asked a very
good question so thank you so much thank
you yes thank you
yes okay uh let us take a question from
Mr Chetan Kumar hello
sir are you there
sir uh can't hear you
you uh sorry I was on mute can you hear
me now I can hear you now yes sir please
go ahead yes sorry so I actually wanted
to understand why there the West doesn't
like Western People their leaders or
even like just the intelligency of the
West don't understand Russia as a
country like I am someone who lives in
the nordi I travel like quite frequently
to Russia because of this family TI uh
and uh a lot of Western People my
friends who are like finish or Swedish
they think of Russia some kind of white
supremacist racist country but I have
never experienced at least white
supremacy from Russia and I actually
travel a lot by road because I like
driving my car to different countries it
is one of my like Hobbies you can say
and Russia is the only border crossing
where I don't feel singled out for being
Indian or being brown but I have felt it
like even I went to Ukraine where you
know they let all the Western European
passport holders pass through like it
was couple like before the war and then
you were singled out to for further
investigation but Russia is the only
country where also the French or the
British passport holders were made to
stand with me for equal number of
questions that than I was but somehow
these Western people especially like
young people they think of Russia as
some white supremacist country and I
cannot just reconcile uh why this is yes
yes it's a very good question that you
asked and very interesting observations
that you made so this is called the
power of propaganda okay okay uh the
West portrays Russia as a nation that is
U that is a propagandist nation right uh
but the fact is that the Western
propaganda is unmatched there is no
nothing that can come close to the power
of Western propaganda they own all the
media Outlets they own the entertainment
industry they own everybody and the same
narrative is is is is put forth every
time about Russia the West understands
Russia very well okay they understand
Russia very well but they want to
portray a certain image of Russia
because Russia is a challenger to
Western Supremacy and hegemony Russia is
well Russia when I was a kid I thought
of Russia as a European nation okay but
today you will see Russia being clubbed
with the East so Russia is now looked
upon as an Eastern nation even though
Vladimir Putin has had blonde hair and
blue eyes but they'll say his eyes are
slightly small so he's an Asiatic or
something you know that sort of thing um
uh so when it comes to Russia they
definitely as far as even I know I don't
see any any racism there they are a very
multi-ethnic Society the dominant group
is obviously the Slavic people but uh
there is a there is there are all these
other layers of society which are all
intermingled the the tatars are there
tat tatars are Central Asian people
turkic people then you have the chash
you have so many ethnic groups that are
are not white uh classical white or or
even European and they all exist coexist
harmoniously in Russian Society so
Russia is the last Nation I would
portray as racist but or or white
supremacist because many of them are not
white of course right but yeah this is
the power of Western propaganda and they
seek to demonize Russia as much as
possible because Russia is the bad guy
Russia is the guy that invaded Ukraine
without any provocation apparently so if
you want to uh if you want to go all out
against a country you have to portray
them you have to demonize them as much
as possible and that's why this happens
but I completely agree with you U when
it comes to Russia there's no racism or
white supremacy they they are and
especially towards Indians Indians they
very friendly so yeah you are absolutely
right all right thank you yes thank you
thank you so much thank you so much
thank you for the question nice meeting
you
okay uh if you want to be on the screen
I'm going to have to see your faces
otherwise I cannot take you so okay
let's take a question from Mr maneda
hello
hello yes you're audible now yes sir
please go
hello uh great fan sir nice to meet you
thank you so much thank you what's your
question uh sir I had actually I I had a
question about the uh nuclear reforms
which are honorable Finance Minister
proposed today to aim for 100 gaw
capacity up to 2035 and installing for
light capacity reactors this year so how
feasible do you think that 100 gaw
Target is and even is 100 gaw enough
from a nuclear Source especially with
our thorium reserves and our extensive
energy needs as we are a growing
country and does even India have the
technological and Industrial capacity to
uh you know have that have those kind of
large capacity nuclear reactors and even
the four nuclear reactors they are
planning to install this
year great question I haven't seen that
portion of the budget I actually haven't
seen the budget so I would not be able
to comment on what has been announced
today but uh let's talk about that's a
very good point that you raise about
nuclear capacity 100 gaws or whatever so
I don't know if 100 gaws would be enough
but let's talk about
percentages see if you look at a nation
like France approximately 60 or 70% of
their electricity generation is nuclear
in origin and nuclear power is an
extremely if you do it right it's
extremely St safe it's extremely stable
and uh it can be a GameChanger it it has
essentially zero carbon footprint so
even if we talk about green energy
nuclear is a great option and India when
it comes to us we have an issue when it
comes to procuring uranium uranium we
have to import from other countries but
when it comes to thorium we have the
world's largest reserves like you
mentioned of thorium the monite Sands in
various parts of India so we have about
I don't know about at least a third of
the entire world's thorium reserves so
uh I'm glad that this was announced
today and I'm glad that the government
of India is serious about going forward
with um with the nuclear program uh
what's said noise I think
20 yeah so let me continue I was hearing
some Noise Okay so I'm glad the Indian
government is serious about this now do
we have the technological capability to
do this we absolutely have it uh we have
this three-stage nuclear program we are
entering the second stage just barely
entering the second stage of the nuclear
program I think if the funding is
provided and the right number of
scientists and the right scientists uh
and engineers and technicians are put on
this Mission then we definitely can
achieve whatever we want to achieve and
when it comes to the thorium program
I believe India has the world's most
advanced thorium research program uh so
I don't think we are short on capability
or skill or ability the only thing we
are sh on possibly is uh political will
and if the political will is there now
then there's no there's no question
about us achieving whatever objectives
we have I would say we should try and
emulate what the french have done they
have a very very high quality nuclear uh
Power program very safe reactors and
that's that's the Benchmark that should
Inspire us so I think it's definitely
very possible for us to achieve these
targets as long as the funding is
provided and and the scientists and
Engineers are given a free hand to do
what they needed what they're required
to do so yes I'm I'm I'm pretty
optimistic about this all right thank
you sir great question thank you nice
meeting you thank you thank you thank
you okay let's take a question from
Bender nyak hello
sir can't hear you please unmute
yourself uh sorry uh I cannot hear you
sir okay we'll go to somebody else we'll
go to somebody else we'll uh he can come
back when he gets his thing right uh
let's go to Mr RT
hello can't hear you you're muted
okay it's not
working
hello is it
working yes I can hear you now please go
ahead sir ask a question what's your
name sir where are you
from uh yes sir basically I'm from Pune
uh my name is Rohan sir nice to meet you
sir please ask a question yes yes thank
you thank you sir actually I do have a
question on uh uh the aircrafts that we
are the thing that we are doing nowadays
like as you say hyper power like America
those guys are also using just F18 for
the Navies and uh F22 and F-15 for the
Air Force I guess so why there is more
diversification on our Indian side that
we are using migs also we are using
Rafal also we are using Jaguars mirages
why this diversification if someone like
me who who does not have background of
defense and all those things I can pick
this things so why don't our senior
people I guess from the defense uh are
not able to pick this is there any y
yeah yeah very good question so we have
kind of like a zoo of various kinds of
animals in our Air Force we have the
Jaguars we have the Mig 21s we had the
uh we had the Maru in the past we we
have the sukko 30 mkis we have the Rafal
and whatever else we have like a
menagerie of various kinds of aircraft
and if you have so many aircraft then
it's it's a headache to maintain them
all so I think look we know how things
were in the past okay it is alleged that
there were lots of Defense deals in
which allegedly government and officials
Etc would allegedly get Kickbacks and
all that that's the story we have all
heard uh so that can that can explain
why we did not uh focus on developing
indigenous aircraft even though we had
the technology like the marut we killed
the program and we kept on buying peace
meal few here few there from various
countries so that explains it so and
there is this element of short termism
in India we don't look at things from a
30-year 50-year perspective we want to
think about the next 5 years because
it's that's the inherent nature of
electoral politics you are elected for
five years and you will want to do
whatever you can in whichever way
possible in those five years only
because once again after five years you
to go and ask for votes so what did I do
in this five years so if you look at jet
engine programs if you look at fighter
jet programs these things that take 10
15 20 years to mature and if you say
that I started this program but nothing
has come out thus far T tangible then
the the common people may not understand
it because our education system has
ensured that people don't
understand the these more complex Nuance
things and that's why we are in the
situation so what needs to happen is
that we need to invest in our own jet
engine program and we need to invest in
our own fighter jet program and the
thing is we if if we are not able to
develop a jet engine then in a short
period of time or let's say in the next
5 10 years then we should acquire this
technology by buying it from somebody
and it doesn't matter how much it cost
costs and it doesn't have to be the best
technology in the world it has to be
decent technology so you know like you
mentioned the Americans have the bulk of
their Air Force is f16s and F5s the f40s
also Tom Cats and whatnot and only a few
of the aircraft that they have are the
f-22s and the f-35s the majority of the
Air Force is those older aircraft that
go back to the 1970s and those are good
enough to do most of the work so we
should
initially have the philosophy of let's
learn to walk before we can run and
let's run walk to learn to walk before
we can fly so
we should get good enough technology and
we should then have large numbers of
aircraft because we have this shortfall
of the number of squadrons the uh number
that we need is 36 or something and we
have I don't know 20 something squadrons
so we have a significant shortfall of
the number of aircraft the Air Force
needs uh so yeah these are the issues we
need to think longterm and uh and we
don't I I get the feeling sometimes that
the uh that the military of the Indian
military wants the best of the possible
things in the world I I have the
specifications which which surpass the
specifications of most American aircraft
and that's what I want let's not think
that way let's let's have decent
aircraft initially in large numbers of
those and then iteratively make it
better and better that's the philosophy
that you would need to have ideally uh
so I'm sure that hopefully things will
go in that direction going forward but
yeah thus far it's been like that so I I
hope that answers your question right
sure sure thank you thank you very much
thank you thank you very much nice to
meet you
sir okay uh let us go to Mr Aran Agarwal
hello uh hello sir uh can you hear me
good evening sir can hear you yes good
evening sir I've been a huge fan of
yours and I I wanted to say uh you're
amazing I I just gave my gate exam today
I uh gate exam uh so I was going to ask
some questions about the mastering
like Masters uh masters of technology in
India please ask one question please ask
one question yeah yeah yeah just one
question so why is why is the like the
quality of people who come from Masters
so so low right so and the programs are
not even good the programs are very bad
and I don't think many people even want
to do Masters if they usually have a job
in btech I wanted to join Dro that's why
I gave gate I want to do something from
artificial intelligence to improve
something there so thank you sir yeah so
first of all uh all the best for your
results whenever they come yeah uh so
why is the quality of the uh students
that pass out of M uh master's degree
programs so bad and you kind of answered
your question by saying that the quality
of the programs is terrible right our
education system unfortunately you know
you know we have the most brilliant
people on the planet in in in this
country in India and uh the situation is
such that the first of all the education
system is terrible so if you turn out to
be successful in life you you succeed
despite the education system not because
of the education system and typically
you'll find that people who get great
very high marks and all many of them
don't do well in life and typically
people who did not do very well
academically they end up excelling in
life and so on um so first of all the
quality of the education system is is
terrible the of the education system
first of all it depends on the syllabus
secondly it depends on the teachers and
third it depends on the institutions and
all three are subpar unfortunately the
syllabus if you look at technical
subjects it's sometimes 20 years be
behind where we are today
technologically uh when it comes to the
the teachers they are mired in the 20th
century mindset of of of of root
repetition and and memorization and you
you essentially study to pass exam not
to actually gain skills so these are the
issues that we are facing and because of
that the output you know the this the
people who pass out of these master
degree programs most of them don't have
the skills it's not their fault they are
victims they are not the problem they
are victimized by the education system
and this is why things like this end up
happening so we need educational reforms
that's what we need and then what
happens is that after you pass out of
the education
system what happens is that uh uh you
don't have the opportunities you you
know you you don't have the
opportunities like if you we do we have
sufficient uh uh avenues for highly
qualified highly talented people to get
jobs or or get employment there also is
a problem so these are all the problems
that we are facing and that needs
long-term reforms in India and as far as
I know the long-term reforms haven't
really started the uh what is it called
uh the new education policy has been
implemented but I don't see really it
actually address adding the core issues
that we are facing so that's the
challenge we face in India today and
that's why most really talented people
they leave the country as soon as
possible and how can we blame them so
yeah that's the situation right now but
one can be optimistic that you know
going forward hopefully soon enough
degrees will not be mandatory for
getting jobs hopefully as the economy
grows we will have more job
opportunities we will need more
entrepreneurs more people of all kinds
of skills and hopefully see if I am
running a business I will not care what
your degree is I will just look at the
kind of skills you have and even if you
are just 10th pass as long as you have
the skills then I'll hire you so
hopefully more people adopt this
approach towards hiring and then the
education system you can just bypass it
hopefully so yeah that that that could
be the solution for us going forward in
the absence of other reforms anyway
great question and very nice meeting you
sir thank you thank you sir thank you
sir thank
you okay let's take a question from from
uh from
Atul hello sir sir can you hear me I can
hear you
yes
from sir I I to ask a question sir do
you think the government our current
Indian government need more appreciation
for the infrastructure development
because in our state coning for example
in our state Kerala we didn't even have
a proper uh t road for the past 75 years
only after like 6 years before they
started having six Line Road that is
National from across all the districts
of Kerala before that we don't even had
a proper Ro in our state so do you think
they much more appreciation development
for of our
country uh I could not get everything
you're saying but you're talking about
infrastructure development and what the
government is doing um obviously uh
infrastructure is critical for a nation
for a country and uh India has had this
very poor infrastructure for a very long
time uh and the current government the
Mr modi's government has has had this
very massive INF infrastructure push
it's initially you have to do just very
basic infrastructure like constructing
roads highways railway lines more
airports and all that so that's being
been happening when it comes to various
States a lot of the infrastructure
development is it comes under the State
government's perview uh so when it comes
to in interstate highways and all
Interstate railway lines and all that
the government the central government
can definitely do that but when it comes
to uh infrastructure development within
a state from one city to another city or
one town to another town I think a lot
of that comes under the state
government's perview and that's where
some states unfortunately we see them
still lagging behind the other states uh
I'm not sure of the situation in Kerala
but I'm glad to hear that now things are
changing that's what you're saying I
hope and we would like to see that
happen more we would like to see every
every Highway being at least a six six
Lane Highway we suppose definitely can
do that and we we definitely need more
airports more railway lines more ports
all of that so uh yeah that's the
direction in which the country needs to
go forward absolutely all
right all right thank you so much thank
you so much sir good thank you for the
question okay those of you who uh I will
need see your faces in order to take you
on the live chat otherwise I cannot so
I'll take the the next person I'll take
will be Mr Karthik but hello sir good
evening hi sir good evening and it's so
good to meet you finally so I have a
question how Russians yeah I have a
question how Russians perceive uh their
internal politics because as I
understand Russia is probably insulated
from the Western propaganda and the
population is not divided into this
level left and right uh so how do they
pursue the Ral politics and how
insulated are they from all these
divisions something I want to understand
the hyalis how is it over
there okay I could not get half the
question but you're talking about
Russian politics and how do Russians
perceive their own politics because
they're insulated from the Western
propaganda and all that right that's
what you're saying yes yes that's yeah
so uh okay so uh Russians if if you see
look the the Western propaganda say that
Putin is a monster he's a dictator he's
a bad guy right and um he needs to go
and ideally the West would like regime
change in Russia but uh as far as I can
see Mr Putin is extremely popular in
Russia and uh the Russian
U ever since the spatial military
operation started in Ukraine in in
February 22 and Russia has been under
siege from the West all kinds of
sanctions and all the Russian and and
the Russian economy has still been able
to more or less withstand all this
entire Onslaught you can see that the
Russian population is becoming more
patriotic more nationalistic and they
are all rallying behind their leader Mr
Putin so that is something that's
definitely very visible and that that
must be something that uh the West
doesn't want to happen but that's
happening uh when it comes to the
internal politics of Russia I'm not sure
it's it's kind of not very clear uh one
thing one question that many people
would probably have is that after Mr
Putin who comes next right right he has
been the leader of Russia for at least
for about a quarter Century now U with a
with a small detour in between when Mr M
became president uh but he essentially
has even then was behind the scenes the
most powerful leader politician in
Russia so he is in his 70s now Mr Putin
and who comes after him is the question
and right now I don't have clarity about
who comes after him because there are
various leaders in VAR political leaders
in Russia but one cannot see the next
Putin emerging from there maybe there is
somebody maybe there are people with
those capabilities but right now we are
not able to see So eventually the
transation of power whenever it happens
I'm sure Mr Putin will take care of it
but yeah so internal politics I don't
think there's a lot of internal politics
in in Russia the kind of internal
politics we have in India the Indian
political system is extremely vibrant
extremely chaotic elections every three
weeks here and there that's not the case
in Russia so it's a very different
political system but overall I see the
people of Russia they are all extremely
nationalistic and the most of them are
rallying behind Mr Putin that's the way
I see it all
right all right sir thank you so much
for your question nice nice having you
here thank
you okay let us uh go with Mr
pushkar hello sir good evening can't
hear you can't hear
you hello sir
hello it's been a pleasure meeting you
so my question is despite having so much
importance in world
history uh India has like older
civilization oldest
language uh exceptional trade 5,000
years ago why it's not that popular in
the mainstream media as we compare to
Egypt or China so it's my S question
okay okay very good
question so why is why is India not
popular
right in the global mainstream media you
will see that
Western the Western media Western
entertainment industry Western
historians Western writers Etc they will
sing the Praises of ancient Greek
civilization ancient Egyptian
civilization um Mesopotamian
civilization even Chinese civilization
but they will say very bad things about
India India is terrible blah blah all
that stuff right the question is why so
we have to understand the difference
between Indian civilization and for
example Greek or Egyptian or
Mesopotamian or suian or Chinese
civilization or even Japanese
civilization what's the
difference the
difference is that Egyptian civilization
is dead it's been destroyed it's
defeated suian civilization long gone
Assyrian civilization Babylonian
Mesopotamian civil ization long gone
Greek civilization doesn't exist
anymore Japanese civilization it's under
Us control and occupation Chinese
civilization well the Chinese Communist
party isn't exactly a great uh guardian
of Chinese civilization they tried their
best to destroy Chinese civilization and
the Chinese Communist party if you see
their officials of if you their leaders
they wear Western dresses and they act
like Western people but yeah these days
there is this talk about Chinese history
and all that these days so all these
cultures that the West
extols are either destroyed defeated or
or hardly
alive that's the difference when it
comes to us despite 1,000 years of
operation OCC foreign occupation and
everything else we are still alive we
are still kicking we are still on
walking on our two feet and we are
actually even uh showing signs of of
growing and Rising again so that's what
they don't like they don't like it the
Western Civilization is an abrahamic
civilization they don't like polytheists
they don't like anything that has
something to do with polytheism uh
that's why South Korea is almost
entirely now christianized and and who
whoever is not Christian is most of them
are now atheists and similar stuff is
happening unfortunately in Japan as well
we are the only ancient polytheistic
culture that survives and we are the
oldest of the lot and that's why they
don't like it and that's why they try
their best to denigrate us and portray
us in a very poor light so if that's the
view that the West has of India and the
mainstream media has of India I think
you should take it as a compliment that
they hate us because we have refused to
die and we are still alive and we are
still Rising once again after a thousand
years so it's actually a good sign and
that's why they don't like us all right
sir very good question yeah good
question thank you very much nice
meeting you thank
okay let's uh go
to Mr pranay Kumar hello
sir hello sir yeah good to meet you sir
good to meet you sir I wanted to ask you
the question that why is the West aiding
and abating the rise of Islam in Europe
so much uh the the Islamic people are
very United
andent and dying Christians and they
want to destroy America so why is USA
helping them and helping Islam grow so
much uh interesting question so first of
all we have to understand that uh Islam
is one of the three major one of the
three abrahamic religions um and the
people who believe in the abrahamic
religions they're called people of the
book so Islam isn't that different from
Christianity or or Judaism of course
there are all these controversies and
lots of things but overall the three
religions are very similar they may look
different cosmetically and from from
that perspective but the core
fundamental tenants are very similar and
they also share many of the same
prophets and all that so that's the
first thing we to understand it's a very
similar religion Islam is not a
polytheistic religion like us that's
that that will never be allowed in the
west they will never told that so there
is that okay now some things don't make
sense uh when it comes to all those
grooming gangs in the UK who that have
been victimizing English girls why was
that allowed to happen for decades when
everybody knew about this we don't know
so some questions only the Western
leaders can answer uh why they are
allowing so much foreign immigration
into their countries and essentially uh
the numbers are growing have grown a lot
in the past few decades and the the
local people the indigenous people now
feel very strongly threatened by the
influx of foreigners uh so I don't think
that issue has anything to do with
religion I may be wrong maybe it does
I'm not sure but why have the chosen
yeah it is it is indeed true that they
have not brought in millions of Hindus
or SS into the countries they have
brought in mainly millions of people
from the West Asian countries and nor in
various African countries into into
Europe so why they are doing it are they
trying to Stamp Out Christianity and
replace it with Islam I am not sure it
looks like the try they want to do that
but what the motivations could be even I
am not really sure what the motivations
could be why would you do that why would
you have your own country your own
people your own culture replaced with
another ethnic another bunch of ethnic
groups and another religion uh I it
beats me it baffles me and I don't have
the straightforward answer to that
question it's it's something that's
really baffling it's like the West is
digging its own grave it's like that so
I don't know we'll see yes sir it is
very confusing to me because Islam
treats Christianity and America like its
enemy
and us is helping their
enemy well that's that's maybe that's
the yeah so it's definitely very
baffling and I myself don't have the
answer to that I myself really baffled
okay all right anyway thank you so much
for your question and nice
meeting thank
you okay
okay let us go to Mr pral hello
sir
hello hi sir can you hear me yes I can
finally hear you yes sir can can you
hear me
sir yes sir I can
hello yeah yes sir I just have a
question sir like uh why I mean we know
that we are into it industry and most of
most of the people from India get into
USA as H1B Visa candidate and uh but the
Chinese have got into deep I mean deep
seek how is that sir how is that working
but uh we are not
uh okay how are the Chinese able to
develop deep seek and why has no Indian
company or entity developed deep seek
deep seek well I don't think that has
anything to do with the H1B issue at all
okay first of all uh yeah lots of
Indians go to the US on h1v visas and
lots of Indians are in the US
technological industry in Sil Silicon
Valley lots of Indians are CEOs of very
major very powerful very large companies
in the US and so on and even Chinese
Chinese CEOs aren't there but lots of
Chinese employees uh are definitely
present in the US and many of them are
on H1B Visas so the H1B Visa issue isn't
probably relevant to the to the
development of fund of of foundational
AI models so the Americans have a bunch
of foundational AI models like uh chat
GPT uh and the per no not perplexity
it's a rapper U Cloe is there and there
are others as well now the Chinese have
sprung a surprise by by coming up with
deep seek R1 and and other models are
also coming out so why is India not able
to develop this is the question that
essentially you were
asking so what it takes to develop a
foundational AI model is you need a lot
see the the way to do it technology
technically is is pretty well understood
what you need is a very large amount of
computing power you need a whole bunch
of of high-end
gpus and you need the right people so if
you essentially take 20 to
50 uh well qualified uh uh engineers and
you give them the computing power that
they need then they will be a then they
can definitely come up with a
foundational AI model in let's say six
months it's very possible but the one
see the thing that's uh holding India
back right now is that the computing
power is very expensive CPUs won't cut
it you need gpus and you need really
highend and very powerful gpus so if you
need let's say 10,000 gpus NV gpus
so if you need 10,000 Nvidia gpus
highend gpus it will cost you I don't
know a few million dollars maybe 10 20
whatever million dollars maybe more than
that and then you need to have that
funding and then you need to have the
right people so that that convergence is
not happening in India so see there are
lots of Indian Engineers it Specialists
or whatever you want to call them who
have the skills to develop on their own
this sort of system what they're lacking
is the gpos and these gpos are very
expensive so here's what needs to happen
actually okay I think today Mr ashni VN
today yesterday whenever he announced
that India will have its own Foundation
model in the next six to nine months or
something like that he said six to next
one year or so so what needs to happen
is that the government needs to identify
teams of people or call upon people to
to contribute to the effort and put
together teams of people and give them
as much competing power they need and
then use the open source uh deep seek R1
uh uh you know that that thing or or
what or you can develop your own
foundational model and build upon on
that another thing we could do is why
not have a competition excuse me among
the top 10
iits you have IIT all across the country
let's take take the top 10 iits and have
every IIT form a team of let's say 20 to
50 students who will work on the project
and you give them as much computing
power need and give them one year to
come up with the foundational AI model
and let's have a competition between the
top 10 I and let's see which performs
the best and let then we can have this
competition done every year and we can
iteratively build upon and improve upon
the foundational AI models the solutions
are simple all you need is a bunch of
talented people in one place for maximum
six months and you give them all the
resources they need and then India will
will come up with 20 50 foundational AI
models so that's definitely possible if
you make the resources available see
today computing power is extremely uh
it's extremely expensive in the past Ram
was extremely expensive in the 1960s 1
GB of RAM was unheard of today 1 GB of
RAM costs nothing so it's very possible
that in 20 30 years the kind of
computing power to that costs that today
costs $10 million will cost tens of
dollars and then anybody will be able to
build these foundational a models
anybody with the right skills will be
able to build it but right now it's very
expensive and that is the one thing
that's that's holding India back so the
government needs to get involved let the
I get involved let Indian entrepreneurs
ones who have the access to the money
and resources why don't they also put
together teams and do that so that's
happening with
uh uh that's that's beginning to happen
now in India Zoho is is now going in
that direction and so on so I think we
need to uh not get too defe about this
okay it's it's a matter of a few months
in which we can have our own
foundational aals I think it's going to
start happening uh sooner rather than
later so I think we need to be
optimistic and I am pretty sure that by
the time this year is out we will have
at least a few Indian foundational a
models so I'm optimistic about this all
right sir but great question that you
asked thank you thank you thank you nice
meeting you
bye okay let's go to Mr Anuj hello
sir hello hello hello sir am I
audible yes yes you're audible it's very
it's a it's a pleasure to meet you sir
I'm such a big fan of yours I've been
following you for like three years now
yeah so I'm from Himachal Pradesh sir so
my uh my question is regarding photons s
like uh what gives photons that speed
like we say that light is the speed
limit of the universe it's a universal
speed limit so what is that inherent uh
thing in in the photons that propels
them at that
speed okay photons uh see it's like this
the way the universe
is any any object or any particle that
has zero Mass Zer
Mass I'm GNA have to mute you sir okay
okay yeah so the way the universe is
every particle that has zero Mass
automatically travels at the speed of
light that is something that is built
into the source code of the universe
let's say so people talk about the the
the the uh uh what is it that the
universe is uh a simulation right the
simulation hypothesis so see we know
that everything underlying everything in
the universe we have mathematics
mathematics is the language of physics
and it is something that underlies
mathematics is a representation of the
regularities and patterns that underly
the universe so if the universe is a
simulation then the it was coded in the
language of mathematics and in the
source code is is inbuilt this thing
that any particle that has zero mass
will automatically travel at the speed
of light nothing is propelling it or
impelling it okay it just travels at the
speed of light now a
photon and and different particles will
have different energies so photons come
in various colors what we perceive as
colors this is red this is white and so
on so the color of the photon is the way
we perceive it we we it is it is matched
to its frequency frequency or wavelength
and that's why we perceive colors but uh
it's just a property of the
universe but so it's just an inil
property of the universe the
universe mean right from the very
beginning since the create since its
creation uh it had that speed inbuilt
into it from the first instant that the
Universe was created the photons and all
the mass massless particles traveled at
the speed of light so that's that's just
an inherent property of the
universe there is nothing that imps them
it's just the way it
is all right all right sir thank you so
much thank you so much thank you so much
thanks a lot
yeah let us go to Tush hello
sir hello am I audible you are audible
yes yeah Namaste sir how are you Namaste
good good nice to meet you my hi my
question is the education system doesn't
teach us how to achieve our desires in
college it's just that a system is there
you bu hard two three hours before the
exam and your answer and come so we
don't feel the need to learn over there
so if we have a constructive desire for
example Financial Freedom or anything
like making a AI system or anything or
making a rocket so how do you learn how
to achieve that like what's the process
how do you yeah yeah you're absolutely
right the the education system doesn't
teach us the very fundamentals of of
succeeding in life how to manage
finances How to Succeed In what you want
to do and all that how do you how do you
learn that you have to go beyond the
education system the information the
knowledge is available out there it's
available in the form of various books
it's available in the form of YouTube
channels and videos how to succeed in
life and how to achieve your things some
of the things that are involved in being
a high achiever are things like
discipline things like time management
things about self-management and all
that so these are skills that can be
learned and these skills are available
in books and on various YouTube channels
so you have to study that you have to
find extra time out of your studies
beyond your studies and invest some time
out of your day or week in learning
these things personal finance is
extremely important it's crucial to
succeed and have succeed in life and and
do well to to generate wealth and build
wealth for yourself and your family and
for the country eventually obviously so
that is important and uh yeah how to be
disciplined how to create systems to
manage your life to manage your day to
manage your time all that so all these
things are merely skills important skill
what's the most important skill in all
of this the most important skill in all
of this I would say is self-management
which is understanding yourself first of
all we are all very Unique Individuals
but most of us don't even understand who
we are are so you to understand who you
are you to understand what your what
your strengths and weaknesses are and
you to understand what you are really
meant to do in life you have a certain
set of qualities and and characteristics
that will ensure that you will be good
at certain things so you to identify
that and then you to work on that and
then how to set goals and how to manage
yourself manage your time all that so
this is called self-management I think
that's the most important skill and that
obviously is not something you can learn
over a weekend or something takes time
you to invest like a couple of years in
that and over time you learn you start
understanding who you are and you learn
these techniques and start applying them
so this is something everybody ideally
should go through the education system
doesn't teach us that but everybody
needs to invest the time in learning
these things much of this information is
available for free on YouTube or you can
purchase reasonably inexpensive books
and buy and and you recommend a
particular book for like how to think
like how to think about all these things
the way you told me yeah I can books I I
can't think of any such books right now
I've read so many books and I've read
self-help books also in the past but
can't many things like hit and trial try
this try that a lot of different what
you should no hit and miss is not good
what you should do is if you want to buy
a book for example let's say book of
time management or whatever it is go to
Amazon look at that topic and find the
best books in that the books with over
100 reviews with at least four star
reviews so if you can that way you can
refine your search criteria and
hopefully you'll find the right books so
hit and miss will take a lot of time you
should be smarter in in selecting the
books or or whatever and that's how you
do it all right I have a small
suggestion sir for the sir no
suggestions no questions lots of people
are waiting you can put the suggestion
in the comments okay please do that I
I'll look I'll definitely look into it
thank you so much thank you thank you
thank you thank
you okay let us go to Mr swastic
hello
sir sir you're muted please yes you're
audible now first of all thanks for
doing whatever you're
doing and everything
and internal politics Rel
financially weak
background
and so I don't
so don't you
think that way we can eliminate the
system G very good question uh so what
you're asking is about the reservations
system and all that right uh so system
so that we can eliminate the so-called
cast system and give everybody the
same you know the same kind of
opportunities and all
that the reservation system is based on
cast it's based on cast until the late
19th century there was no official cast
in
India
dat and after 1947 what's happened is
that the government ensures that in all
your import certificates and documents
cast is mentioned birth certificate
School living certificate school all the
major certificates and that ensures that
you are tied to a certain cast and then
when the reservation system started
mundle commission 1990s whenever it was
uh it was all done on the basis of cast
that so and so casts will be given
reservations and other cast will not be
given reservations but what happens is
that there are many casts or many people
belonging to so-called backward cast or
whatever cast who get reservations but
many of some of them it's possible are
very financially well off very rich and
they get benefits that could have gone
to somebody else so what you so I agree
with what you're saying that
reservations I don't think it's entirely
a bad idea but it should be done on the
basis of your family's Financial
condition if your family is below the
poverty line or below a certain set of
criteria then you should be given
reservations not on the basis of cast
and reservations should not be something
that that goes on for hundreds of years
you should solve the problem you're
trying to solve in the next 20 30 years
maximum and then end reservations by the
time if if everybody is reasonably uh
well off and and there are no people
hopefully below the poverty line then
you don't need to do this the problem is
that we have institutionalized cast we
the politicians say that cast system is
bad and all that but they are
institutionalizing cast by by by forcing
us to have so-called cast in all our
documents we need to destroy cast inate
cast and the simplest way of doing it is
to make sure that no document contains
the word cast no mention of cast and
give reservations if required only on
the basis of financial status that's the
solution Simple Solution but the
politicians will not let this happen
because they benefit from these things
and they are keeping us divided as a
society that's the problem one of the
major problems we're facing in this
country and then we all see everybody as
what cast what cast what cast that's
it sir so how can we start uh or maybe
you know to change this thing the
mindset of people we can't government
has to do this take the step and only
then things will happen apart from that
I don't they will not but see I don't
think there is any cism to a very large
extent in the country go to any
restaurant do you care who has cooked
your meal no no no no you go to the you
go to the bus station you go to the
train station go to the airport does
anybody care what the cast is of the
next person no one cares this is a
non-issue we the PO want this to be
issue so that they can divide the
country by cast and then you know play
cast Bank vote Bank politics that's the
issue solution is very simple we need
better
leadership strong leadership all right
thank you so much for the question thank
you thank you sir thank you for having
me have a good night sir thank you you
too
bye okay let us go to Mr anmol tapa good
evening sir hi sir pleasure to meet you
can you hear me yes I can hear you nice
to meet you yes sir so my question is
regarding like uh China and India we
have been parallel Civilizations for
almost 5,000 years now uh we being 5,500
years old and they being around 4,000
years old so both of us has seen uh many
world conquering civilizations like the
Persians the Arabs the Turks the British
the Portuguese so where is it that we
lagged in the modern era and the Chinese
excelled and uh how can we overcome the
backwardness that are currently
in okay okay the yeah so first of all I
would say that we are not just 5,500
years old we are the oldest civilization
that that that is known to have existed
we don't know how old our civilization
is if your archaeologist will only dig
up to a certain level they will say okay
it's only 5,000 6,000 years old but you
to dig until you find so-called virgin
Earth which is no more artifacts of
human evidence but they don't do it but
look our civilization is at least 10,000
years old if you look at the old indust
Valley site that is that is birana it's
almost 10,000 years old and so on so
that's a different point the question is
U when it comes to Western uh Empires I
would not call them civilizations I
would call them Empires the Roman Empire
is an example they conquered so much of
the so much of the western world and the
Chinese also did conquest to a certain
extent all where did we fall
behind um we also did conquer in the
past but we are not taught about this
for example L mapa conquered much of
Central Asia uh Chandra Gupta II of the
Gupta dynasty also conquered bajik and
various parts of Central Asia kishka the
great our one of our greatest Emperors
conquered a territory all the way from
the Aral SE to the Caspian Sea to
present day shinjang and parts of Tibet
in in present day China so we've had all
these Conquest we not taught about this
where did we go wrong in the past 1,000
years we became probably too civilized
we thought that everybody will follow
the rules that we follow in Warfare and
that and people don't do that we were
not practical enough pragmatic enough
and we were not unified as as an as a
sub as a subcontinent there have been
times when the subcontinent was unified
under a single emperor that those were
the times when India did really really
well like the uh morian era like the
kusan era the Gupta era even the cha era
was great for Southern India and all
that so what you need is unification
political unification you need practical
pragmatic approach to wordss
international relations don't be
idealistic that everybody will behave
the way we behave and you need to
prioritize economic and Military might
that's what needs to happen so those are
the things uh that went wrong in the
past 10,000 years the most important
thing is political Unity under a single
single centralized government even today
we don't have that we have too much
decentralization too much federalism in
India so these are some of the things
that uh went wrong and that's what those
are the lessons of History we can learn
all right sir so like I want I would
like to say like the China opted for
like an authoritarian regime so is it
like right to say that for a developing
Nation democracy is not as good uh for
it's not good you need at least 20 30
years of dictatorship or centralized
government very very strong yeah so I
agree with you y That's my question that
all right all right thank you so much
nice meeting you sir thank
you let's go to Mr Nan chabra hello
sir hello yeah hi sir am I audible yes
sir you're audible yes sir nice to meet
you and I really appreciate the
knowledge that you give so sir my
question is on one hand the Trump
Administration talks about drill baby
drill they give out slogans like these
and they back out of the Paris agreement
and on the other hand these guys are uh
trying to get Greenland and they say
that climate change is not real but at
the level of actions they are trying to
do something in which they are perhaps
demonstrating that climate change will
happen uh ice caps will melt and they
need Greenland so that they can make a
trade route out of that and so my
question regarding this is now these
guys also have the social media in their
hands and with this the there's a great
difficulty in separating political
propaganda from scientific facts they
two get mixed into each other a lot
especially with climate change as a
topic so with social media in their
hands how can one separate political
propaganda and scientific facts so that
they can get to the truth and build
solutions for the real
problem yeah yeah good question how do
you uh separate fact from propag
propaganda especially when it comes to
science for that it's very simple you
need scientific literacy so you can tell
for yourself whether this whatever is
being claimed is correct or not right
you need scientific Literacy for that
basic scientific literacy uh how to
think from first principles and things
like that uh and you have to understand
one thing very clearly when somebody
says trust the science that person is
most likely a fraud because you don't
science you don't do science by trusting
what you're told you do science by
questioning
everything questioning yes everything
has to be interrogated it has to be
proven without any doubt so if a new
claim is made you have to interrogate it
you cannot trust it because some great
expert has made it many of these great
experts are are on the payroll of the
government or or or some Corporation or
something if you look at the history of
the United States in the 1950s and 1960s
medical doctors were promoting
cigarettes okay medical doctors they
would say that so and so cigarette is
the best in the world and that's the
best I that's the one I prefer to smoke
and all that so these people the the
pharmaceutical industry the medical
industry has a long track record of
being on the payroll of whoever will pay
the money and if if some great famous
accomplished doctor or medical expert
will make a Mak a certain claim another
example is the US Standard diet or
whatever they call it okay there is this
diet that is prescribed in the US which
for the longest time is prescribed an
overload of carbohydrates which is what
makes people fat eating fat doesn't make
you fat eating too much carbs make you
makes you fat and eating too much sugar
makes you fat and fat and gives you
diabetes but the American Medical
Association has been promoting sugar for
such a long time for decades so you
cannot trust these people you cannot
trust these medical professionals phal
industry you to question every claim
they make to the right way to do science
is by questioning not by trusting when
somebody says trust the science that's a
short short almost short short example
that this person is has a certain agenda
so now how to differentiate fact from
from propaganda look you need to develop
scientific literacy every I think I know
the education system is terrible and all
that we can keep on crying until until
the life is over my point is that if the
education system is is problematic it
doesn't teach you science then why don't
you teach yourself science today all the
basic basics of science can be learned
online if you want for free nobody is
going to charge you money for that so I
think in incumbent it's a respon
responsibility of every citizen to learn
certain skills and acquire basic
scientific literacy on their own so that
they can make their own uh validation of
various claims that's what I would say
all right
sir thank you thank you very good
question you asked thank you so
much okay Mr nikit
Dev hello
sir sir huge fan
thank you so much thank you uh so my
question is Sir how do you have like
such a huge arsenal of knowledge for
example we as a student students if we
have to like uh research on a particular
topic or some other thing on our own so
like how what do you suggest about that
because like you I think you have
knowledge in like every
subject not every subject but uh yeah I
so how do you do this right as a student
see what happens when you are a student
is that you have
these uh often very horrible textbooks
that you have to take you to study them
memorize them and very often the
textbooks are written unless you're
lucky very often the textbooks are
written by a writer who is not very good
and if it's a scientific subject you
need to understand the flow I mean if if
you have a derivation of of a certain
law of physics or equation you have to
be able to see how it was derived and
often they will say the derivation is
Les left is an exercise for the reader
and that sort of thing and sometimes
things don't flow at all so very often
the textbooks are very boring they they
are very difficult to to read from and
all don't you end up feeling tortured
and you don't learn anything that's what
happens I also went through the same
thing what do you think of course I went
through that so how did I acquire
whatever little knowledge I have I was
always super curious and uh I used to
treat Library time as fun time so
nothing was more interesting for me than
spending a day at the library and I
would read whatever my curiosity to took
me towards so I would read about history
I would read about crystals I would read
about um films how special effects are
made in Hollywood films you know Lucas
film they had this thing called
industrial Light and Magic a studio
called called in ilm so I used I read
about that so I used to read about all
kinds of stuff I was inherently a very
curious person and that's how and and
the thing is this even if you're reading
something that is potentially an
interesting topic it's possible that the
textbook or the book you're reading may
not be that interesting and it may not
give you all the value that you need so
you when you are reading something when
you're studying something you should
have the philosophy that it's okay to
forget it's okay to forget if I'm
reading let's say 20 Pages it's okay to
forget 18 Pages at least I remember what
I found interesting and that's how you
build upon on your knowledge so that's
always been my philosophy that's how I
do it and obviously there are tools and
techniques for memorization which uh are
short-term tools and techniques they
will not help you in the long run so
that's that's always been my Approach
and that's how I have learned whatever
I've learned all right sir thank you
thank you thank you so much thank you so
much nice to meet you thank
you okay let us go with Mr zishan zi
hello sir yes can you hear me I can hear
you yes so uh you said in the past that
you think the United States is the most
powerful country that's ever existed uh
so obviously you cannot achieve this
without uh having great leaders
throughout your history so my question
is uh in each Century the 21st 20th and
19th century uh which US president do
you think was the best of that century
and why considering a accomplishment in
Legacy okay that's a great question I
haven't had this one before good so
let's start with the 19th century I
think the greatest American president of
the 19th century was most likely Abraham
Lincoln and why is that he fought to
keep the country unified I think the
South seceded legally from from the
United States okay from the union it was
not an illegal SEC secession it was
according to the Constitution and the
laws but Abraham Lincoln said nothing
doing I'm not going to let this happen
and he went to war to ensure that the
union survives intact and as a whole so
I think 19th century Abraham Lincoln was
the greatest the 20th century who was
the greatest uh who was the guy at the
end of the second world war it was Teddy
Roswell wasn't
it
Frankin Franklin Roswell I think he is
the guy who was the greatest of the 20th
century and why is that it's he who set
up the global Empire the seeds and the
roots of the global Empire it is he who
ensured that the United States did not
withdraw withdraw from Japan and in
other parts of the world that they had
uh you could say uh you know created
military bases they stayed there and
then he expanded this and this was
carried forward by subsequent US
Presidents by by signing all these
so-called treaties which are essentially
uh all kinds of Alliance treaties with
with Nations like Japan with South Korea
even Pakistan which essentially
vassalized all these nations and made
them client states of the us so that is
so that that is something that
tremendously contributed to American
power in the 20th century so I would say
uh Roosevelt Franklin Roosevelt was the
architect of that
21st century I haven't seen any great
news president thus far so I don't know
we'll see maybe Trump is the guy we'll
see about
that all right thank you for answering
sir
DC big fan nice me you thank you thank
you so much
bye okay sushant de sir how are you sir
I'm good sir uh how are you I'm good
nice to meet you okay so my question is
uh a few days ago I went online out of
curiosity I uh searched uh which of the
defense system
uh either India or Israel have a better
defense system because uh technically
Israel has the iron do right uh which is
similar to what I've heard the
description of anti balistic
missile so I just want to ask which one
uh uh which defense system uh either
India's or Israel's defense system uh is
techn technologically more advanced or
better because there are a lot of
Defense systems that India have but
Israel don't but online when I checked I
got mixed responses uh they say how can
you compare Israel Israel is like uh
really Advanced and uh they have
invested in technology for like a lot a
lot longer than India so which defense
system uh on uh in the battlefield is uh
uh in Battlefield is stronger or more
technologically advanced okay so you're
talking about missile defense systems so
when we talking about missile defense
systems there are we have to understand
there are various kinds of missiles
there are cruise missiles there are
ballistic missiles there are missiles
that have maneuverable capabilities
after re-entry as a ballistic Miss and
so on so forth various kinds of missiles
exist in the world and if you have a
missile defense system ideally you want
your missile defense system system to be
able to take care of all of those but
the world is very complicated the
trajectories are very different when it
comes to ballistic missiles Cru missiles
short range ballistic missiles medium-
range ballistic missiles long range
icbms and so on it's very complicated
and then you have maneuverable re-entry
vehicles mvs and then you have mirvs
very complex now we talking about two
Nations Israel and India Israel has what
you rightly mentioned is the Iron Dome
system we understand that it's a very
good system but even that is
not it's it's not fail proof we saw lots
of Israeli Iranian missiles impacting on
Israeli targets right so one thing first
of all you to understand that if you
want to defeat a missile defense system
it's just a matter of pure mathematics a
missile defense system will have a
certain number of missiles to take out
your incoming missiles okay and it can
take out let's say x number of missiles
per minute all you have to do is fire X
plus1 number of missiles per minute and
you've defeated the missile system and
if they have let's say 2,000 missiles
for defense you fire more than 2,000
then there's nothing they can do okay
what you also have to consider is the
amount is is the territory you're
defending Israel is a small tiny Nation
they're defending a very small territory
so they have that inherent advantage
that it's only this much territory we
have to defend and everything else we
don't care about when it comes to India
we are a sub continent it's a gigantic
territory when it's the US once again
it's a gigantic territory now what kind
of missile defense systems does India
have first of all we have bought
purchased the the S400 from Russia which
is said to be probably one of the best
missile defense systems of its of its
kind in the world it can take out cruise
missiles it can take out U those
artillery Rockets kind of kind of
rockets it can also potentially take out
certain kinds of ballistic missiles
that's what it's I think is the
strongest and fastest if I'm not which
one a five I think is the strongest and
fastest India
has that is not a defensive missile
that's an offensive missile sir that's a
different thing the ug5 is an offensive
missile it's not a defensive we talking
about missile defense system right yes
yes so the S400 is what we have I don't
know how many we have and we cannot put
them all over the place all over the
country so we will only deploy them
where at sensitive uh look
where you really want to defend the
place like New Delhi for example and so
on uh we are also developing our own two
stage missile defense system the p a
prvi advanced demonstrator missile is
there and and you have an EXO
atmospheric missile
defense exoatmospheric missile and so
one missile takes out a Target outside
the atmosphere in in in space and
another one is a more short reaction
missile which takes out missile which is
within the atmosphere and not far from
the target so we are in the process of
developing our own indigenous system
maybe in 10 20 years we'll have
something which is superior to the S400
500 system perhaps uh but right now it's
a work in progress so if you want to
compare Israel and India I think Israel
because of the advantage they have of
very small territory I think they
overall have a more effective missile
defense system but India we have the the
constraint of or or rather the the thing
that we have very gigantic territory so
it's very difficult to defend every
square kilometer of it so that is a
disadvantage we have but obviously the
enemy doesn't want to land missiles in
forests and jungles and mountains they
want to hit cities right so that's where
we will obviously focus our defense on
so right now it's a work in progress I
think in 10 20 years we'll have our own
indigenous systems that are like world
class that's where we stand right now
all right sir yes thank you thank you
thank you nice meeting you thank you so
much okay uh let us see who all we have
let us go to Mr buma sua pan hello hello
sir am I audible yes sir you're
audible so my question is um in your
early videos you have so much hope for
India's uh future after watching your
recent videos uh I having def mindset is
it over for our country and our
civilization
so is it over for India is it over for
Barat is it over for our civilization
it's not absolutely not see times change
the conditions in the world the
circumstances in the world were
different in 1990 and they were
different in 2000 they're different in
2010 they were different in 2019 and
then we knew that in 2020 something very
drastic happened the pandemic and the
circumstances changed again and today
the circumstan have changed once again
we have a very different kind of world
leader Mr Donald Trump and he's going to
approach the world in a certain set of
ways and so it's not over for India it
is it is I think it's very probable that
he will try and turn India into an
American vasal that'll be the best
possible outcome for the US and for
Donald Trump it'll be the greatest
achievement probably probably that can
that he can
have um so that's what the Americans
will try and it is also probable that we
may have to play along with that to a
certain extent but does it mean it's
over for India obvious obviously it's
not over for India we have seen such
terrible times in the past 10,000 years
and we are still here right we still
here we survived the past 1,000 or so
years of foreign
occupation right now it's possible that
we may have to become quazi vasal for
some time of the US but that's not
foreign occupation so I think we have to
think long term maybe the next four
years will be interesting maybe the next
10 years may be interesting but we are a
civilization that has endured thousands
of years and we will certainly endure
the next several thousand years uh it's
true that certain things that should
have happened in the past 10 12 years
have not entirely happened many reforms
could have happened that haven't quite
happened that way education system how
many uh new ships did we build in the
past 10 years I'm not very satisfied
with the number of ship naval ships we
built submarines we are lacking aircraft
we are lacking so there are things we
lacking at but there are things that are
very positive as well so I would say
that we should not be defeatist we
should be optimistic India as a nation
with a tremendous amount of potential we
have a one of the best leaders we've
ever had in the past 100 years who's the
prime minister right now so we should be
optimistic yeah Nations go through tough
time sometimes but it is it is not uh
something that should make you defeatist
and all pessimistic I think the future
remains bright for us all right sir
thank you s thank you so much thank
you okay let us go to Mr vun prajapati
how are you
sir am I audible sir yes sir you are
okay first of all thank you sir and uh
my question is about the the system of
governance you know uh India and China
we got independent at roughly the same
time and we adopted this m multi-party
multicolor democratic system and and and
I learned from you that we historically
had the chakrawarti Samra type of
democracy so we are habitate to this
kind of democracy Al when I see often at
China I feel like the one party system
had done then great has done them great
wonder mean in 70 years the Chinese are
competing with the us they they winning
hundreds of gold medals in Olympics they
have the best of military such a big
economy so um the overall question is
the current democratic system in India
efficient enough or we should no it is
not efficient enough it is the wrong
system for India we chose the wrong
system in 1947 or 1950 or whenever it is
1947 we became a dominan state in 1950
or whenever it was we became a republic
we chose the wrong system I am not
saying we should have a dictatorship and
we should have an emperor and all that
it's okay to have a democracy but why
not the presidential system the larger
your nation is the more centralized the
overall power structure has to be the
smaller your nation is the more
decentralized you can make it so we are
a gigantic Nation a subcontinent sized
nation and we chose a system that
emerged and evolved on a small island in
the Atlantic called
England okay this democratic system the
Westminster democracy the parliamentary
system it evolved and emerged emerged
and evolved in in England and that is a
very small little nation and it is
imminently unsuitable for a gigantic
subcontinent sized Nation like India we
should have had the presidential system
but now this system the Westminster
system is so deeply entrenched and every
single politician who is in power
anywhere has benefited from the system
so they will not let it go so I don't
know what the solution is but right now
we are saddled we are burdened with an
extremely inefficient system that that
pulls us P pulls us back and and and
weighs us down if we had had something
like the Chinese system then we would
have been ahead of China that is a
guarantee and like you rightly mentioned
historically we did not have this sort
of stupid system we historically had
Emperors and you would have democracy
locally at the low levels but at the
central level would have no democracy
the emperor was the king for life and
that's how it was and generally we had
good
Emperors uh so yeah the system so the
answer to your question is that we have
not chosen the right system we have
chosen a very poor system which is not
suitable for our
civilization all
right thank you all right thank you nice
to meet
you let us go to Mr tanai Desh Pandi
hello
not suitable for our
simp
right hello sir can you hear
me I can't hear
you hello okay we'll take you later uh
let us go to Mr scand hello sir Hello
nice to meet you sir nice to meet you as
well I can hear you so so my question is
what is really happening in the US uh
recently in the past 4 days uh there
have been like uh two airplane crashes
so what is really happening one of them
was a military
helicopter I don't know what's happening
that's a good question what on Earth is
happening in the United States you have
this uh uh passenger aircraft that's
trying to land in Washington DC over the
pmac river and it's slammed into by a
military Black hop Blackhawk helicopter
that's flying way above where it should
be flying the ceiling in that area for
Blackhawk helicopters military
helicopters is 200 ft and this thing was
flying much above that even Trump
tweeted that that the helicopter was
flying above the the altitude where it
was supposed to fly and this helicopter
just goes straight into the aircraft and
the aircraft plummets into the poac
river and I think nobody survived so
there was a couple of days ago and then
one more plane crash I think in
Philadelphia wherever it was
Philadelphia yeah Lear jet or something
that crashed somewhere at 500 kilometers
per hour or something I don't know
what's happening it's very strange I
mean I would not venture to speculate as
to what is happening and what could be
behind this is it all uh just accidents
or is it something more Sinister I don't
know uh I don't have the information to
about this way or that way but it is
definitely suspicious and strange that
you have so many accidents in such a
short period of time in the US which is
the well the technologically most
advanced nation in the world so it is
definitely strange and it is definitely
uh something that everybody is remarking
upon so yeah I agree with you it's
strange all right thank you sir thank
you thank
you yeah let's go to Mr Rohit thear
hello sir uh hello sir it's an honor to
meet you thank you sir sir recently
China uh unveil their sixth generation
fighter
aircraft uh but uh I'm skeptic uh
skeptical about uh their abilities uh
are they really that good or uh I mean I
think the F22 Raptor uh for me is still
the best out there I think the it is
part of a Chinese
propaganda uh yeah good question you
know what every nation indulges in
propaganda any every nation that aspires
to be a great power or wants to be at
the top most level will will indulge in
every kind of possible
propaganda uh you make an interesting
point about the F22 Raptor I would say
it is superior to the F35 I agree with
you the F22 Raptor is probably the best
aircraft that's ever been built thus far
yeah now when it comes to the Chinese
six generation fighter plane uh well
it's interesting it has three engines
and it has that that uh typical stealy
uh set of characteristics and all and uh
they claim it's a sixth generation
fighter plane and so on so I would say
first of all congratulations China you
are doing great but I'm not sure how
great this aircraft is I'm sure it has
some characteristics that would classify
it as a sixth generation fighter plane
and which is definitely something that
other nations haven't done thus far so
that definitely I would have one has to
congratulate them for that achievement
but I'm not sure how great it is
obviously there's going to be a lot of
propaganda there's going to be a bunch
of tall claims at the end of the day how
good an aircraft
is can only be determined when you see
it in combat so until that that happens
it's it's just talk you know so I agree
with you I I am I am on the on the same
side as you I am skeptical about the
claims about how great thecraft is I
think it remains to be seen how good it
is but it's definitely a significant uh
technological leap that they have uh
achieved right yes thank you thank you
so much sir thank thank you so much for
your
question let's go to Mr aush hello sir
hello a sir how are you I'm good how are
you doing
sir I'm doing fine and my question is
recently NASA conducted a study and they
found on EST there was a presence of
complex molecular uh things and we all
know that for life to evolve in
evolution the complex molecule played a
very important part so my question is
given this studies what do you give the
probability to the pens spia hypothesis
I think you are familiar with the
hypothesis and what do you think is the
most optimal solution for the farmy
Paradox okay you ask me two questions
let's talk about the uh pans what is
panspermia first of all for the benefit
of the audience panspermia is this
Theory or hypothesis that the building
blocks of life are scattered across the
universe and according to this
hypothesis maybe about four and a half
or three or whatever four billion years
ago the building blocks of life appeared
on Earth through asteroid or Comet
impacts which means that these asteroids
or comets were they they contained the
building blocks of life and that's how
life was Seated on earth now when we
talk about the building block of life in
the panspermia hypothesis we're talking
about DNA actually DNA because if you
look at the rate at which DNA mutates
and doubles in doubles in size and
complexity you know at what rough rate
it happens and if you go back in time to
the simplest possible DNA that takes you
back about 10 billion billion billion
years yeah but we this planet is about
4.4 billion years old so it doesn't make
sense how can DNA evolve so fast so yeah
that is definitely a big mystery and
that's why this hypothesis has been has
been put forth the pantp hypothesis that
maybe DNA and the building blocks of
life came from outer space okay that
that is panspermia now you what you're
mentioning let's talk about that so uh
an asteroid sample or something was done
some study was done of an asteroid and
they detected the presence of complex
amino acids on the asteroid amino acids
are the building blocks of proteins and
proteins are the building blocks of life
I mean much of the human body and all
animal bodies are made of proteins
proteins fats Etc that's what most
animals most organisms have so without
proteins there's no life and without
amino acids there's no protein and the
our genome tells protein I mean it it
tells you how proteins how to code and
all that so we have discovered complex
amino acids the basic building blocks of
of proteins and life on an asterid what
does it mean so it's not very surprising
we have had many more um you know people
have have analyzed meteorite samples and
all on which theyve discovered amino
acids and complex organ organic
molecules so it's not the first time
this has happened but in in this case
what you're talking about I think
they've discovered all the major amino
acids which makes it which makes the
which which gives more strength and more
Credence to this hypothesis of
panspermia uh so yeah it doesn't but it
doesn't prove that life came from
outside Earth it just tells you that
these complex molecules seem to be quite
widespread and prevalent in our uh
asteroid belt and maybe beyond our solar
system also it's possible so it's an
interesting development but it doesn't
answer any question definitively it
doesn't Okay the question about yeah
that's what I thought yeah
yeah all right sir thank you very much
for the question very interesting
question thank you thank you nice
meeting you thank you thankk
you okay let us go to Mr Amon George Mr
Aman George hello hello sir it's a great
pleasure to meet you sir so my question
how did Germany able to achieve such a
significant technological advancement
during World War I despite having the
back in World War
I yeah good question how did Germany
develop such advanced
technology uh which helped it so much
militarily during World War II despite
having a very massive setback in World
War I in which they were defeated and
humiliated right so that's a great
question very great question it takes
you back to the fundamentals of how you
develop technology from scratch so
Germany okay you go back in history
before 1871 there was no Germany there
was no Kingdom called Germany there was
no Empire called Germany Germany was
created as was unified and a new nation
was created in 1871 by the Iron
Chancellor Otto bismar and this new
nation which was entirely new it was
eager to prove that it belonged on the
big stage on the big league in Europe so
they really pushed uh they really uh
what what do you say they invested in
science and technology and research and
development they set up great institutes
in which they found the best talent and
promoted the talent like anything so you
had great professors like Lu F boltzman
like Max plank Etc who were the heads of
various institutes and and the best
possible Talent was was uh recruited and
promoted and they emphasized research
and development of all kinds of
Technologies for example one of the
technologies that gave birth to the to
the field of quantum mechanics was uh
you know the light bulb the light bulb
had been invented but scientists did not
and Engineers did not understand how
what was the correlation between the
temperature and intensity of light and
the color of light and that was one of
the big Mysteries that could potentially
make a nation the best best uh you know
uh the nation that made the best light
bulbs so it was this question that gave
birth to the to the field of quantum
mechanics so Germany was at the
Forefront of all this it it it
prioritized Merit it funded all the
right research and that's how in a very
short time in just like a few decades
Germany became an industrial superpower
it became the major industrial power in
Europe and at the Forefront of all the
Cutting Edge Technologies of its time
now it did suffer a massive defeat at
the end of World War I and it lost
territory and it was humiliated in the
treaty ofai and all that but its
industrial base kind of did not get
destroyed in World War I and that's how
they were able to build the Technologies
needed for Adolf Hitler to start World
War II and they developed some of the
most Cutting Edge Technologies ever
Germany was the nation that developed
the first ballistic missile the first
cruise missile the first jet engine and
so much more it's because they
prioritized Merit and they funded the
right research and they promoted the
best talent that's why they were able to
do this it's a very interesting question
right thank you sir okay thank you so
much thank
you let us go to um Whom Shall we take
let's go to to Mr adiya G gavani
hello good evening sir honor to meet you
nice to meet you sir thank you uh so so
my question relates to the decline of
the USSR in 1991 so sir as you also
mentioned multiple times that the USSR
was the was was Us's primary competitor
as a superpower in the 20th century uh
what were some of the mistakes that the
USSR made that eventually culminated in
its decline in 1991 and what do you
think that India can learn from
this very good question very good
question what are the things that
contributed to the decline of the USSR
and its dissolution in 19991 wherever it
is so when a nation when when an Empire
Falls it doesn't fall overnight the the
problems they start accumulating decades
before the actual eventual demise
happens so there are many things that
went wrong it was overall a decline of
Standards grow slow gradual decline of
standards in the USSR after Joseph
Stalin died the decline started
essentially okay Joseph Stalin was well
whatever his faults and shortcomings are
okay there were many but he was a great
Visionary leader of the USSR he is the
guy who set up the industrial base of
the USSR and made this nation in a short
period of time after 1945 a superpower
okay he is a guy responsible for that
Joseph Salin but after he died the slow
decline started
uh and the industrial base did not uh
stick to the highest technological
standards for example one of the biggest
uh um inventions of the 20th century was
the computer okay and once you have a
computer you want to make it more and
more powerful and that gives rise to
super computers so when it came to the
race for super Computing the Soviets
started falling behind the US and by the
time you come to the 1980s they were
like 10 15 years behind the US in terms
of super Computing uh technology um and
then when it comes to the Space Race
initially the the Soviets were far ahead
of the US they achieved all the firsts
in the Space Race but after the
Americans reached the moon before the
Soviets it for some reason the space
exploration and the space Technologies
it took a back foot the Soviets were the
first to send a probe to the surface of
Venus from which it was able to take
photographs and record sound that is a
technological feat that I don't think
anybody can anyone can do even today but
they were able to do it in the 1960s 70s
whenever it was but over time the uh
maybe it was a lack of political will
lack of political whatever but over time
I think the the Soviet leadership
started looking
inwards and the standards declined and
uh so it was a gradual thing overall the
nation and the other thing that led to
the decline of and eventual dissolution
of the of the USSR is that the Americans
controlled the Seas they had created
this gigantic network of military bases
all across the world starting with from
the end of the second world war and they
controlled all the Seas all the choke
points the Su Canal U the gulf the
malaka strait the various choke points
in in the Sea of Japan and so on and
they were able to the Americans through
their propaganda were able to
successfully project this image of being
the superior power of being the more
open society and the Soviets started
looking inwards so because the Americans
started controlling all the trade routes
all the C routes all the choke points
that definitely constrained the USSR and
its potential it's its ability to grow
economically and trade with the rest of
the world so all of these factors I'm
sure there are more as well these all
all these factors contributed overall
cumulatively to the decline of the USSR
another example of the decline of the
USSR technologically is what happened in
chernobil 1986 I mean it was just a it
it should not have happened so all these
things contributed to the eventual
dissolution of the USSR but I would put
it down to declining standards slowly
slowly erosion of Standards which
eventually became unsustainable that's
what happened all right so thank you so
much for your question thank you nice
meeting you thank you
sir uh let us go to Mr Shankar karney
hello sir hi sir am I audible you are
audible yes yeah so I'm a history BFF I
keep on reading about great emperor and
and ruler so it's I have a question so
Ian the terrible Katherine the Great
Peter the Great Alexander one Joseph
tanel and Vladimir Putin who do you
think is the greatest Russian leader of
all time judging Putin on his current
performance and part two is where do you
see Russia going in the coming decade
and in the coming century
become more insignificant or actually
they would rise further and thanks for
having me it's an honor to talk to
you all right thank you nice to meet you
as well so uh who is the greatest
Russian leader of all time uh many
choices like you mentioned many many
examples Katherine the Great by the way
she was German but she married the
Russian sa and became the Empress of
Russia she is a great cont Contender
uh uh Ian the terrible obviously he was
terrible and he did very crazy things
but he was also one of the greats um I
think it boils down to maybe two three
people Putin I mean the way he had the
country recover from the disaster of the
dissolution of the USSR and what he has
been able to achieve but Russia isn't a
great nation today it's not a superpower
again it is a near superpower thanks to
its nuclear Arsenal but yeah it is it is
not anywhere close to where the USSR was
but it's been a significant recovery
under Mr Putin so that that counts in
his favor
probably probably cathine the great may
be the the greatest Russian ruler of all
time ironically being of German
ethnicity probably she's the one um and
when it comes to where Russia goes going
going forward it all depends on the
eventual transfer of power from Mr Putin
to his successor if that goes right
there's no clear succession succession
as of now we don't know who might uh be
the next success of of Mr Putin yeah we
don't know as of now we don't know who
could be on his mind or whatever but if
if the succession see he's he's in his
70s now it's going to be 10 years at
most after which he will have to pass on
the baon to somebody else so if he gets
the succession right and if his
successor takes Russia even further
towards greatness then we'll probably
remember Putin as Putin the great
because he's the guy who started the
turnaround uh I think Russia if they
play their cards right they could be
the great one of the great powers of the
of of the century they have all the
resources they need territorial
resources mineral resources everything
they need they they're Anarchy so I
think um if they play their cards right
right now the whole world is tacked up
against them but if but they still are
are enduring right now they're able to
resist they're able to still stand
strong and their econom is actually
growing so if they play the cards right
they could end up being one of the top
203 or four powers of the 21st century
right thank you that's a very
interesting question question thank you
thank you thank
you okay so let us go to Mr aayush
takur hello sir Namaste sir am I audible
Namaste yes sir you audible uh sir so
like my my question is that like I am a
astronomic Enthusiast and like I want to
start as astrophotography so like how
can I start astrophotography with a
smartphone like some basic guides you
can
suggest well well well I'm I'm really
glad that you are interested in
astronomy and
astrophotography I personally have never
done it as a kid I always wanted to have
a telescope by but it so happens that
until today I've never owned a telescope
okay uh so there's that when it comes to
astrophotography with a mobile phone I
not sure how you would do that you would
need a very very high-end mobile phone
um and then you would need to be able to
zoom I don't know minimum 20 times or
something 20x Zoom I would say maybe
100x Zoom if you want to capture the the
the the crators on the moon or to be
able to resolve the the rings of Saturn
uh you need a good resolving power on
your instrument what asop photographers
do is that they get themselves a decent
telescope ideally a powerful telescope
and then you need some you use something
like a DSLR or something that you attach
to the telescope and then that's how you
do it uh I'm not sure how you would do
it with a cell phone I'm sure it's
possible to a certain extent I'm sure
you can at least capture reasonably good
images of the moon I've never tried it
maybe I'll I'll try it after this live
stream ends I'll try it out maybe but
yeah I'm not an expert in this so I
would not be able able to give you very
specific
actionable uh advice but uh I'm sure
there's resources available online as to
how to do it perhaps like using perhaps
using the telescope and like the
smartphone to that like whenever that is
definitely yeah so you would need a
telescope and in addition to a
smartphone and then you will need
something to to you know have the two to
integrate the two together yeah yeah
yeah thanks a lot sir all right thank
you thank you nice meeting you sir thank
you okay let's go to Mr anay Kane
hello hi sir am I
audible your sound is very
low oh is
it uh okay I'll just speak
loudly so yeah my question is that uh so
in India you know that politicians they
have like a sense of entitlement in
general they think that they
are uh more than or they have they are
very great and the same is true about
even bureaucrats and government
employees and police so what do you
think can be done to end that the sense
of
entitlement well you would need a very
powerful and strong leader who can get
the bureaucrats in line and uh you know
see one thing that really really works
in favor of the bureaucrats is that you
can fire them no matter what they do
whether they indulge in corruption or do
something very bad or whatever you
cannot fire them you you can at most
suspend them you know when when you hear
the news it happens all the time that so
and so bureaucrat was caught with so and
so money and bribes and all that that
person is suspended that s that person
is not dismissed or terminated from from
employment they only suspended which
means that after a few months they come
back so they essentially have a job for
life and it's because of some Clause of
the Constitution of India or something
like that so and if the government tries
to revoke that Clause then all the
bureaucrats will go on strike and the
country will no longer function so
that's the kind of choke hold they have
I'm not saying they are all bad the
bureaucrats I'm sure there are some of
them who are really good but um so
that's a very problematic structural
issue that dates back to the roots of
the Indian civil services we call it the
IAS right Indian administrative services
but originally it was called the Indian
civil service by the British and the IAS
is nothing but a continuation of the
British Indian civil service and they
constructed it in such a way that it's
ended up being what it is today uh so
you would need a you would need a very
strong leader a very very powerful
leader who can dismantle the system and
and reform it thoroughly from the bottom
of up and top down and uh yeah I mean
you would need a leader with probably
dictatorial powers to to make it happen
you know but right now that's not the
case and when it comes to politicians
it's once again the kind of system that
we have that uh technically they serve
the nation and they serve the people but
in in reality they actually rule over
the nation so that's just the way it is
that's why I was discussing earlier in
the in today's live stream that you know
we chose the wrong system for our
country and this system is weighing us
down is it is slowing us down if we can
if we could have reached I mean you know
India could have grown much faster and
much better much better with a different
kind of system but that's just what we
have so we have to do whatever we can
despite the
system
right all right sir thank you so much
for your question thank you nice meeting
you
right okay let's go to Mr sidhart hello
uh hello sir can you um hear me I can
hear you yes um yeah so a big fan
firstly um absolute pleasure talk to you
U my question is um on the line of
illegal immigration that's happening
into Europe right so if you basically
look at what's happening it's um
military aged men as you say in your
previous videos military aged men um
with very you know uh with uh very
aggressive mindset coming into Europe
from only specific areas into Europe so
um how does not one but not two
countries but an entire continent fall
prey to um illegal immigration how are
they not able to like open their minds
and think what's going behind the back
because if you look at what's happening
out of everything it's the US that is
benefiting anything bad happens to
Europe it's the um United States that
benefits right if you look at who blew
up the NST stream obviously they won't
tell it directly but there's a clip of
literally Biden telling before it blew
up that we've got ways to blow it up and
then it suddenly blows up and they blame
it on the Russians so anything bad
happens to Europe it essentially goes
back to America so uh do you view
illegal immigration as a way to generate
friction between two ethnic groups or um
what do you what do you say on
this so I'm not sure what they're trying
to achieve by having millions of these
people coming into Europe but why is it
happening and why is none of the
European nations able to do a thing
against this that's the real Crux of the
of the matter you to understand that
when it comes to the European
Union the no democracy there and why do
I say there's no democracy let me
explain
see and there's no sovereignty even more
than democracy there is no sovereignty
when it comes to these nations that are
part of the EU and why do I say that n
that none of these nations are genuinely
Sovereign what are the characteristics
of a Sovereign Nation firstly you print
and control your own
currency secondly you have complete
control over your borders and who come
comes inside and who goes out these are
the two defining characteristics of a
Sovereign Nation and thirdly you get to
decide what happens inside your country
and what rules and what laws are
enforced three characteristics of a
Sovereign Nation in the EU none of the
EU member
states has its own currency they have to
use the euro which is a continuation of
of the dut Mark that's number one
secondly none of these nations has any
control over their borders the borders
are open anybody from any part of the EU
can move into your nation and there's
nothing you can do about it number three
what was the third
thing number three is law laws what laws
are are enforced in a nation well it's
the EU laws that are enforced in the
nation so all of this is being
controlled from Brussels so none of the
EU Nations is a Sovereign Nation they
are all non Sovereign Nations they have
lost their sovereignty so all you have
to do to flood the entirety of the EU
and all the nations within it with
illegal immigrants is to make the
decision from Brussels and who controls
Brussels well the bigger power controls
Brussels is the us so you are right
that's how it is going and that is why
none of these nations is being able has
been successfully able to resist this
tremendous influx of illegal immigrants
now why is this being done why is Europe
being destroyed de-industrialized
there could be many theories for that
one of the things I can think of is that
whenever the Americans think of a strong
Europe they see those they see those
visions of the marching boots in the
Hugo Boss uniforms Nazi uniforms and
they want to ensure it never happens
again so the idea behind the Nazi uh
regime was the idea of the superior race
the AR so-called white Arian Race So if
there is no more Superior race left
they're all mixed up then that can never
happen again so maybe that's the reason
why so you can see that Europe is being
slowed
neutralized de-industrialized and it's
all happening in real time through
illegal immigration and so many other
means and none of these nations are able
to resist that because they are not
sovereign anymore that's why yes if you
look at what quoted no no no follow-up
questions please we have so many people
waiting for it all right thank you so
much very good question thank you
yeah let's go to Mr jatin hello
am I audible sir yes sir you're audible
hello oh Mr J so it's an first it's an
honor to share
the thank you I can hear you sir please
ask a
question oh firstly sir it's an honor to
share thank you sir the
screen uh I have tons of
questions uh I don't know what to ask
you should be prepared let's start with
our neighbor I you can ask me one
question sir one question yeah so I want
to ask about
Nepal
mhm
yeah so are in 2008 there was a royal
massacre in
Nepal yes uh the prince I think dependra
I think dendra yes name what's your
question he killed his yeah yeah he
killed his own royal family and then he
killed
himself and then a Scott Scotland Yard
police came in out of nowhere to
investigate so
what actually happened that night if you
are have any knowledge what happened is
shrouded in mystery the official
narrative is that Prince dendra went
crazy and he killed his own family and
then he shot himself that is the
official narrative now do we have the
real facts has anybody actually gone and
seen what happened nobody knows but I
for for one don't buy this story that
that the prince went crazy and killed
his own own family it's so convenient if
you want to wipe out wipe out the whole
royal family it's so convenient for this
sort of thing to happen at that time the
maoists were fighting the Government of
Nepal and they were trying to form you
know take over the country and then
conveniently and and the nepales
government was the was the RO Royal
government of the royal family because
it was a monarchy right so the royal
family is wiped out Prince G Mr King
gandra comes to power and then he's made
to abdicate so it's very convenient and
it very very conveniently you know ends
the matter so I find it very suspicious
I don't personally believe that this is
what happened maybe there was they were
all eliminated by somebody but I suppose
we will never know so I can't really
give you a definitive answer to your
question but thank you for your question
and nice meeting you sir thank
you uh let's go to Mr Shas okay we have
already crossed two hours maybe I can
take a couple of questions more um let's
go to Mr Shas shety hello sir Namaste
sir nice meeting you nice meeting you my
question is why does Bollywood shows isi
and Pakistan in good light in movies
famous movies such as bangi ban batan
and tiger 3 despite many atrocities they
commit inside and near the bord which is
very
uh yeah interesting uh that Bollywood
has this great love for Pakistan I don't
know what this what the reason is okay
you will you will see that many of these
movies they show Pakistan and India as
brotherly countries and it's only the
politicians who are creating the
divisions but the people they love each
other
and they will show isi agents as kind of
good people and heroes and all that when
isi is a terrorist organization
essentially they are behind the
terrorism they have been behind the
terrorism in in Punjab first and then
Kashmir for decades right and even and
and you will even find that in previous
about decade or so ago until it was
ended they would have Pakistani singers
sing songs in Bollywood movies so
Bollywood has this history and this
track record of of this great love for
Pakistan despite Pakistan bleeding India
for decades through terrorism through
atrocities of of the worst kind and what
explains this I I don't know I I really
don't know what explains this but that's
that's probably one of the reasons why
people don't watch Bollywood movies
anymore and Bollywood is now you know
it's it's it's it's dying a very slow
gradual death very slow because people
are tired of this the they they keep on
promoting and supporting our enemies I
mean if you have a Pakistani singer or
Pakistani actor come and play a role in
a movie they will earn money from us
from our viewers and they will take that
money to Pakistan okay and maybe they're
not supporting terrorism but they will
pay tax to the Pakistan government and
the tax money is used for for supporting
terrorism so why should our people
support Pakistani terrorism I don't get
it so I think that's one of the primary
reasons one of the major reasons why
people anymore maybe that's why and the
triple movies are very famous in as they
show our culture in very good
light yeah maybe maybe but I think now
people are getting uh getting wiser and
that's why Bollywood is no longer the
force it used to be so yeah anyway good
question sir thank you so much nice
meeting you thank you sir thank you
sir let's go to Mr Tushar Singh hello
sir uh I am audible sir hello yes you're
audible okay so a big fan first of all
thank you second I just want to ask like
uh given us acquisition against Chinese
AI firms like deep seek they are
accusing of them uh using uh training
their models using open AI uh responses
okay and also they are like proposing uh
the starget AI in Project like $500
billion project and they would they want
to maintain the AI dominance by
stiffling the competition okay uh so uh
can they actually ban open source model
like deep
seek I think it's impossible to ban
something that's open source but the
point you're making is very interesting
see the the let's talk about chat gbd
okay it's the major major Foundation
model that we have in the market right
now so chat GPT how did it it train its
algorithms how did it what they did was
they scraped the internet of all
possible data including copyrighted data
they must have scanned I don't know
hundreds of thousands of books
copyrighted books and trained their
model on that data and all kinds of
copyrighted content on the internet
scraping it off the internet and and
training their their model on it and
that's how they were able to build the
various versions and iterations of chat
GPD so what they did was well it breaks
copyright but it's okay if they do it
it's perfectly fine if they do it now
the Chinese what they've done is that
they've taken the chat jpt responses up
allegedly and they've trained their deep
seek R1 model on that through a
different method called reinforcement
learning now so so the so Sam Alman is
is complaining that the Chinese have
have done something unethical well what
the Americans did was also unethical
which is like breaking um breaking
copyright and all that the point is uh
the Chinese have have outdone the
Americans by making their model open
source which is great for the rest of
the world for whoever has the resources
to build their own Foundation models you
just can take the open source and and
build on top of that or or or tweak it
if you
want so yeah they've they've Sten a huge
Mar on the US and it's very interesting
that they were able to do it with such
little money5 or $6 million for the
training and whatever it cost for the
gpus 10,000 gpus they had lying around
so they use that and the Americans I
mean they they have this project which
is worth
500 trillion was it billion 500 billion
dollar yeah that's a tremendous amount
of money you you can make a very good
foundational model with such little
money but the Americans JB in all open
they have been they have been consuming
so much money so there's something
definitely wrong with the way the
Americans are doing things and samman
was saying that we need to revise the
social contract now but that won't work
now because the Chinese have given this
whole thing for free uh so yeah that's
the deal it's it's about dual standards
rules for you but not for me that's the
kind of approach the Americans have and
now they are feeling and they want to
you know maintain their Monopoly and
hemony or Technological monopoly over
the world so I'm sure they will stop at
nothing to once again you know get ahead
of China but it is not possible to ban
an open source model it's simply not
possible to do that because open source
anybody can download it and then use it
for it's it's like you know downloading
movies through torrent or whatever it is
is illegal but there's nothing you can
do about
it will always pop up on the Internet so
that's the kind of thing it is you know
so they they will not succeed in Banning
uh open AI models not possible right
thank you sir thank you thank you so
much for your
question okay uh let us take one last
question for today we have gone way past
two hours and I will take it from Mr
vikramaditya RoR hello sir this a great
pleasure sir finally interacting with
you so so my question was like recently
like we have heard Trump has stopped
like a to Pakistan and like Bangladesh
how long will can you think this regime
puppet regime will be able to last and
also there have been like pressure from
like the arakan Army on the on some
border the CH chiong region so like
because I according to me it feels like
it won't they won't be able to last this
four years of Trump's Administration so
how do you see this impact of this Aid
or they will continue to receive funds
from other sources like VES back sources
yes sir okay so the Americans have
stopped Aid to all countries except for
Egypt and Israel so it's not like they
have only targeted Bangladesh I think a
lot of Indian commentators are trying to
you know Mis portray what's happened
Trump has stopped foreign aid to
everybody except for two countries and
this includes stopping of foreign aid to
Bangladesh and whoever else um but look
the fact that Bangladesh Has a puppet
regime that is a puppet of the us it's
going to benefit the Trump regime as
well so I don't see any reason for them
to you know stop funding them through
covert means and I don't think that the
Muhammad government will fall anytime
soon there is all kinds of stuff
happening in Burma it's out of control
the situ situation there there is the
arakan Army and so many other ethnic
groups fighting over there for small
pieces of territory and one hears rumors
that the arakan Army is encroaching upon
Bangladeshi territory from time to time
I'm not sure how true those rumors are
and how well founded they are uh without
having our reporters and and foot and
boots on the ground we don't really know
we have to rely on secondhand
information and and claims so I don't
know about that but I would be very
surprised if the Trump government
completely withdraw support to the
Muhammad yunus regime I mean the
American um Empire superpower is built
on creating these client states wasal
states and once you have that you don't
give it up why would you give it up so I
don't see Trump withdrawing support from
Muhammad news he may say things verbally
but I think the support will continue
through covert means or other means I
think it will continue all right enough
thanks a lot all right thank you so much
thank you so much okay with that I am at
the end of today's live stream
unfortunately I've got so many other
people waiting in the wings I am sorry I
won't be take able to take your
questions I have to end it here so I
apologize to those of you who could not
uh be on the screen and ask me questions
today uh but uh let's see maybe we can
do this again in the future all right so
thank you so much to all of you who
asked me questions thank you so much to
all the viewers for watching and I will
see you next week in next week's live
stream until then take care thank you
very much bye-bye